[Music]
Hello mental health Monday family. I
almost said the wrong thing. Living man
of church family. So I was like wait
mental health Monday family. Hi guys.
Good to see you here. So happy that uh
you guys are with us. I know we missed a
week last week. Good to see you Dr.
White. Good to see you as well. And I am
trying to make this so that I can see
the chat so I can see what people are
saying. Let's All right. How has your
week been, Dr. White? Uh, it has been a
peaceful week, relatively speaking. Uh,
so you know, of course, my mom is
staying with me and my mom can cook, so
it really Yeah, it really makes Oh, is
that right? Yes. It's very therapeutic.
Um, yeah. What are some of the
Panameanian dishes?
um Panameanian dishes it would be like
um especially uh arosfolio, you know,
that kind of stuff. I mean, I don't eat
chicken, but I just if you want it
authentic. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. A lot of
Caribbeans migrated to Panama. I do know
that. So, there is, you know, quite a
bit. So, we do a lot of Jamaican stuff
as well, like ground food, akin
saltfish, you know, all that kind of
stuff. But, oh, I'm impressed. I'm
impressed, Dr. White. She's gangster.
She's gangster. So, you've been So, you
haven't been complaining about mom being
there at all. You're like, "Oh, no. Oh,
you're happy you get to come." Not that
Florence was not already killing it in
the kitchen. I know she was, but you're
just like, you get you get your wife and
your mom's cooking, so you're happy.
Well, Florence has been um studying uh
to pick up her doctorate. Okay. So, uh,
I've kind of like relieved her of
kitchen, you know, requirements, all
that kind of stuff. She's, so she just
has been f focusing on that. So, to have
mom come come behind and provide some
support to both of us, we are very
appreciative. Very, that is amazing.
That's amazing. Well, I want to say
welcome to some of our viewing audience.
And please forgive me if I say this
wrong, but Kamagello, I think it's
Kamageloo. I could be wrong. Um but
welcome u from South Africa and Camello
I think is saying it's 2:05 in the
morning. Wow. Thank you. Thank you for
tuning in to mental health Monday. We
are we are so we feel so privileged to
have you to think of us and to wake up
in the early mornings uh in the country
of South Africa and tune in. We we
really appreciate it. Also Christopher
Andrew is saying hello. So, Christopher,
where are you viewing from? And please,
others, let us know where you're viewing
from and share this link on your social
media. Let others know that you are
watching a mental health program that is
being hosted by two mental health
professionals and that they get to ask
their questions. And our title, our
title, our topic I should say is uh
about alcohol and alcoholism and what
alcohol addiction can do to you. So
definitely share that. Um but let us
know where you're viewing from because
we want to we want to hear from you. We
want to hear from you. I know we took a
week off. Um I had to go and you're
talking about moms. I had to go take
care of my mom. A and um I was in
California for the week, but it was like
I wasn't vacationing. I was working.
You were handling business. Yes. But I
did enjoy being um in California on the
coast. I forgot like I really didn't
bring warm enough clothes because here
in in the south like when it starts to
warm up like it's warm in the evenings,
it's warm in the morning. Like it's just
it's warm, right? I forgot the coastal
how did I forget? I've only been gone
three years. But uh the coastal um
climate when it gets in the evening and
the morning it's chilly and you need
like you have to do layers. So it's
going to heat up during the day, but
you're going to need like a light jacket
during the day. I mean in the morning
and in the evening for sure. Absolutely.
Like it's funny when you live in
California, you always have a jacket
near you no matter what. Always because
the weather just shifts so it shifts.
That coastal breeze is coming in.
Definitely. Okay, Christopher, you're in
Wildwood, Florida. Well, it's good to
have you here and we are so thankful to
have you here and everyone else that is
viewing and watching with us. So, Dr.
White, you had to leave last time. I'm
putting it. you had to leave early. So,
we are wanting to I'm not going to talk
as much today because we want to I
carried it for a little I did carry it
till the end. It was but I definitely
did not have the knowledge that you have
on addiction. So, we want to we want to
hear from you. Um and honestly, I can't
even remember where we left off, but
let's you can you can pick it up. Start
from the you know top. Yes. Because we
really didn't have a lot of time last
time, right? And uh this is sort of like
the it's it's hidden in plain sight. Um
alcohol addiction is often overlooked
because it's kind of talked about so
much you don't think it's that big of a
deal, right? But when you look at the
stats, you realize alcohol is nothing to
ignore. Uh something to take actually
very very seriously. One of the first
questions I asked you was how much do
you think we as a nation spend on
alcohol and that statistic was so like I
don't want to say alarming because
that's a little too strong but I think
most people about fall out of their
chair. You were like uh what do you
think like a billion or something like
that? I think I said 1 billion and you
said way more than that and see I'm not
remembering 4 billion 30 304 billion.
And so what that breaks down to is the
average annual expenditure per customer
unit on alcohol beverage was
$637 up from
$563 in
2022. Okay. So that's almost like the
average, you know, person in the US is
spending that much on alcohol, like 600
bucks.
So, uh, a US household spent on average
$294 on alcoholic beverages consumed at
home. All right? And in the same year,
an average of $343 was spent on
alcoholic beverages consumed away from
home. All
right? So, we are spending a lot of
money. A lot of money. Here's something
really funny. Um,
so as you're going through life, you're
going to be in settings where you get
pressured to drink, right? Where do you
think I got the most pressure to drink?
The most pressure like where you
personally got the most pressure to
drink. The most pressure. Yeah. And it
wasn't college. College. It wasn't
college. It wasn't even high school. Not
even high school. This is Oh, I think I
know what you're going to say. Medical
school.
Not even medical school. What? Like talk
about irony. I was at an addiction
psychiatry conference.
Sitting around with my colleagues. Wow.
And they're ordering all kind of
sophisticated drinks, bourbon, and put
the ice and bring some side water with
it and all this kind of elaborate stuff.
And I'm dying laughing. And so then I'm
like, "Hey man, I'll
take I'll take my standard drink of
virgin pina colada." And I'm like, "And
I don't want her having any experience
whatsoever. I want a virgin pina
colada." So they take my order and um
the waiter leaves and all of them just
launch into me. Why would you order
that? You know, why would you order
that? And it was just so comical like
give me a break, you know? Um why would
that be a problem, you know? So it was
just it was just super super hysterical.
I'm talk about dramatic irony because
you wouldn't think that you'd get
pressure in that kind of a setting. So
it's Right. Well, I know your your liver
thanks you. Oh. Oh man. Your whole body
thanks you, but your liver thanks you.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, so just in terms
of how much we spend and it's it's a
no-brainer because you see how much
alcohol is is is used. It's really
interesting. Yes, it it definitely is.
And so that that we spend in producing
alcohol and then think about all the
advertise or is all the advertisement
that they do for alcohol. All that's
tied into that number. Well, and it's
unfortunate because I mean that's what
you expect an advertisement to do. It
just glorifies it. It just shows all the
good stuff, you know? It puts it at the
center of being attractive and having
friends and it's at the core of it's it
looks fun and elegant for Yeah. for
women. It looks elegant. beautiful
glasses and bottles and I'm just like I
mean and we know a reality that is very
different than that you know in terms of
hey what what actually happens
so just so we talked about how alcohol
is the third leading preventable cause
of death in the US according to the CDC
in 2022 and you said third preventable
third preventable cause of death in the
us preventable guys. Yeah, I want them
to inh
140,000 deaths per year estimated from
alcohol according to the CDC.
Um, and what's interesting about one of
the other statistics is that alcohol is
associated with more
overdoses compared to all the other
drugs combined as far as over including
opiates.
So, it's it's it's it's almost like the
silent killer because like you just I
don't I just don't hear about this kind
of stuff. Um now in terms of traffic
fatalities, what might you think the
number might be? How how many um so
let's say alcohol is let let's say that
there are 30,000 fatalities. Mhm. What
percentage of of that 30,000 do you
think is alcoholrelated?
If there's 30 Say that again. If there's
30 fatalities, if there's 30,000
fatalities Oh, 30,000 fatalities. How
many of them are due to are are
connected to alcohol intoxication?
Half. That's That's not bad. Um, so it's
a third oneird. So alcohol is is
responsible for
10,000 traffic accidents and traffic
fatalities. Traffic fatalities. I
believe that because when you're I mean
people say about drinking responsibil
responsible and always having you know a
driver and all that type of stuff but
when people just aren't do not they're
they're not thinking in that mature wise
mindset. I'm not saying everybody but
obviously the majority or a big chunk
are not thinking that way. They think
and they think they have it. they don't
have a real sense of how intoxicated
they really are and that they should not
be on the road. Well, I mean, there's no
question it impairs decision- making,
you know? I mean, so part of part of the
and and that's why you hear about the
legal limit, but um the obviously the
more that you drink, the more it can
impair your decision-m and so
um it's it's pretty it's pretty
straightforward. Mhm. Um,
what's the what what's I mean I this is
a trick question. I'm trying to figure
out how to um Well, you already said
that my liver would thank me. So, the
liver plays a preeminent role in
clearing the body of
alcohol. Well, what is the function of
the liver? Um, the the liver is the
body's detoxifier. So, a lot of the
medications that we might take, it's the
liver that houses the reactions that are
going to figure out how to
metabolize that substance so that it can
then get out of the body, whether
excrete it in physical waste or sweat it
out of the body or, you know, what have
you. But it's the liver that figures
out, hey, how are we going to get rid of
this, right? Mhm. Um and so you can
imagine then
why a liver that's not working is
incompatible with life.
And and also then it's the reason why
when people um when people drink and
obviously drink too much um it can
result in the condition called you know
cerosis big word for starring of the
liver but basically you're damaging the
liver to the point where it's it's not
functional. Um, and you know, this this
obviously is incompatible with life if
you don't get something like a liver
transplant for, which of course is not
something that's easy necessarily um to
get. Um, we are going to focus on we're
going to shift and and talk about um
treatment in a in a moment, but I I just
wanted us to kind of think through some
of these um statistics, right? Things
that we don't always think about. I
mean, people were pretty blown away when
you um when you read that first or when
you read the statistic about how many um
casualties are from, you know, being,
you know, drunk on on from alcohol um
and causing fatalities. Um and when you
because you're you're about to switch
gears now and you know about treatments
and things like that. But before we even
go right into that, you know, I know
there's people who are viewing um
that have dealt with an alcoholic um in
their life and and are probably just
wondering like what do you what is what
should they do as a friend, a family
member when they're trying to get
somebody who's an alcoholic some help?
Yeah. What should they do and what they
what should they not do?
Well, you and I both know that a
hallmark for therapy and for therapeutic
intervention is first start with
listening. Like listen and get really as
clear as possible as for what is it that
this person needs? What is their stated
need? Do they even recognize that they
have a need? So it it's absolutely
critical that whatever intervention
you're thinking of it start with
assessment. Okay, this is standard in in
in in professional you know interaction.
You start with assessment. You start
with listening. So really and truly try
to get an understanding of what is this
person's stated need. Um do some
listening, ask some good questions. uh
one of the first things that the
assessment will do is it will help you
understand what stage the person is in
and I'm sure um Atante you are familiar
with the stages of change
and this is something that's famous to
motivational interviewing one of the
things you do is you got to see where is
this person where is this person's level
of motivation right because when you
understand that that's when you can
match the intervention
to their given stage of change.
Um, so I would want to listen, but then
I would want professional advice. I
personally especially if I have a person
dealing with something as serious as
alcohol addiction
and we don't know anything about it like
meaning
meaning I wouldn't hesitate to get a
mechanic to get me some advice if my car
broke down. I wouldn't hesitate. I
wouldn't it's like come on like this is
a no-brainer. Um but I think sometimes
with the mental health you know issues
we feel like we can take it on
ourselves like when in fact at the root
of an alcohol addiction is a
neurobiological shift in the mindset
that reorients the brain in a way where
it becomes dependent on alcohol. Right?
like to function. That's that's not
intuitive. That's not intuitive because
what you're thinking is, man, this
person just needs a good prayer session,
you know? Um, and I'm not saying prayer
is going to hurt, right? Right. But we
need to honor the fact that God designed
the body and the
brain to make
changes and and and support the behavior
of your choosing.
So like I I can't tell you how powerful
it is to really think about a brain that
is reoriented around drinking. It's
reoriented. It's now that's its main
thing. That's a powerful thing. And to
think that you can just say, "Ah, stop
doing it." Or, "I don't know anything
about alcohol. I don't know anything
about addiction, but I can cure this
person." Right? That's quite a bit of
hubris. That that's that's quite a bit
of hubris. Um,
so just just be aware of it. And and see
what will happen is while I'm talking
there are people who will be saying to
themselves they'll be like I know
somebody who just quit I know I told
this person again remember how I started
the discussion there are stages of
change and so you'll find different
people in different stages right correct
that doesn't mean that now you have
sufficient perspective to to be able to
say well this this is how most addicts
are going to believe or this is how Most
alcoholics are going to be believe I I
promise you it is a disease that is
deserving of professional attention.
Professional attention. Mhm. And when
you're too close to a situation, like if
it's a spouse or a child or a parent
that the the person who's dealing with
the addiction, they definitely um a lot
of times will resent or fight back to
those people who are so close to them
trying to help them make that change. If
it's someone like um um a mental health
professional or in a different setting
that is they they are more um will be
more obliged to listen and want to at
least hear possibly if they're in that
phase where change is that they're in
that phase of change where it's possible
to make that decision 100%. And let let
me help you understand how complicated
alcoholism or addiction is. There are
skilled practitioners. There are skilled
therapists passionate about therapy who
will say, "Let me get you to somebody
who actually has expertise in dealing
with alcoholism for sure or addiction
because it's a specialized approach. I'm
one of those therapists."
I mean, I and you're skilled. Well, but
and I definitely refer I mean I don't
Yeah, addiction is not my specialty, but
uh definitely refer them to someone who
specializes in that because because
there are just things that are
counterintuitive. All right, I see a
question here. I call alcohol the truth
uh serum. Why do people display their
honest feelings a lot when inebriated?
What one of the things that allows me to
modify my behavior, it allows me to
modify my speech and it allows me to
edit my content is because my
preffrontal cortex is functioning.
So, one of the things that will happen
when people get a damaged prefrontal
cortex is their capacity to filter um
will be impaired and it'll be reduced.
So sometimes people who have a damaged
prefrontal cortex, for example, they
might even be more rageful, but other
times you'll be like, I can't believe
you said that, you know, because the
bluntness is kind of surprising. So one
of the things alcohol will do, and it's
famous for doing, is it will disinhibit.
It will disinhibit. So where you might
have been inhibited before, um, now
you're more prone to just saying that
thing. Um, but as it progresses, one of
the things that you do do is you lose
judgment. You lose the judgment to edit.
Um, and that's why you might be a bit
more truthful. Only problem is it might
be brutally truthful. I hope that was
helpful, Cassie. Yeah. People say when
uh they hear a drunk person saying
things, they believe it. it may have
come not out the right way, but because
of they don't have that that barrier
that would help them to filter, oh,
maybe I shouldn't say this, maybe this
isn't the right time, that they're just
more honest in those type of situations.
So, that makes sense. Um, so Shares is
saying, so it's true once an al Oh, no.
She says, "So, is it true once an
alcoholic always an alcoholic?" Very
good question because people say that
Charice just dropped a bomb in here. For
those who don't know, she just dropped a
bomb where like a lot of people who are
close to the community, they just pull
their chair up because they're like, I
want to see what he's going to say.
Yeah. What you going to say? And I'm
interested what you're going to say.
Okay. So, on this side of the equation,
Sharice, um there's what's called a
12step community. So, like Alcoholics
Anonymous, you know, so on and so forth.
And so the message will be look take
your take your condition seriously and
just presume you're always an alcoholic
because when you do that it'll keep you
humble. It'll keep you coming to the
meetings. It'll keep you disciplined
about your recovery because the mindset
is I can never drop my guard and you
know what that's a good thing. So
there's an advantage to thinking that
way. Also, if you're going into the
community, it's kind of silly to be
like, you know, I'm in the community,
but let me fight with you on this issue.
I don't think it's worth fighting over,
you know, um, as far as, you know, this
label of alcoholism. Okay. Now, over on
my side as a Christian psychiatrist,
right? So number one,
um I recognize that the brain, as I said
before, is capable of orienting itself
around the activity of your choosing.
I'm a firm believer in
neuroplasticity. I believe your brain
can shift itself into new behavior. So
now you're talking neuroscientist as a
as as as as as a believer in
neuroplasticity and and and in
neurobiology. So that I do believe
healing can take place. Now where that's
not helpful is it's unfortunate when a
person says to themselves, I'm healed,
so now I can start now getting sloppy.
That's where it's unfortunate. Um it's
almost like there's there's a hubris,
there's a arrogance where now um I don't
have to be as thorough. That would be
unfortunate. That's where it can be
helpful. But personally, the language I
would embrace is I'm in recovery and
I'll be in recovery forever, but I'm in
recovery. I I think language is so
powerful. I would never want to
pronounce over myself doom. So that's
why I like the language of recovery. I'm
in recovery. But I see the two the two
advantages to both. Yeah, I think that
makes sense. And I think the community
won't be mad at you for that. Most won't
be mad at you for that. Um I mean it's
it's something similar to what I tell
couples, right? It's like especially
when they're ready to graduate from
therapy. um if they stop doing the
things that they have learned to
do, they will be right back where they
were to come in to therapy in the first
place. And so I think it's the same
thing for an addict. Like they are in
recovery. And so that just means that
the lifestyle decisions that have gotten
you to where you are to be uh in
recovery and to be doing so well, you
have to continue to do that um
throughout your life so that um you're
not practicing actively in an addiction
space. So it makes sense. Absolutely.
Absolutely love it, Tim. Love it. I say
I'm recovered in recovery. Um, here's
another statistic that should really
motivate you to take your recovery as
serious as possible. This is a stat
coming from the National Institute of
Health as well as the World Health
Organization.
Heavy drinkers die on average 24 to 28
years earlier than their counterpart,
their non-drinking counterparts. Okay?
So long-term heavy alcohol use can
shorten life expectancy by two to three
decades.
Okay?
Especially when combined with other drug
use um and things like smoking. Okay. So
this this hopefully would have a person
be very motivated. Uh so I I just want
to make sure I was clear in answering
your question. So, if you have a loved
one that is that is suffering with
alcoholism, get some professional
guidance in terms of how should I how
should I tackle this? Um because the
things you might be inclined to do that
you think are helpful might not be
helpful and some of the things that you
might be thinking might be unhelpful
might be helpful. Get some professional
guidance.
[Music]
Mhm. Um I like what I mean I know this
is not up here but I like a comment.
Let's see if we can put it up
there. Let's see. I truly believe and
what he is saying about the
neuroplasticity as someone who is going
through that I can say it takes a lot of
prayer and dedication. And dedication.
Yes. Yeah. Um it it's just I mean it's
the reason I can believe that when a
patient is sitting in front of me
there's hope there's hope. Um there is
there is genuine neuroplastic support
for your transformation. There is you
know what we believe as mental health
professionals as soon as you pick up the
phone that's the beginning of your
healing process. So as soon as you are
you know wanting to reach out for help
that is the very first step and so
that's the beginning of the process. Um
but yeah but let's so okay and I have
well I have a question and maybe others
you know do as well and like what we're
talking about. So,
um, if someone for whatever reason is
not able to get into a rehab situation,
I mean, you know,
and they're not even able to afford, you
know, traditional therapy to stop. What
would you say to that person, but they
want to stop drinking?
First and foremost, I would say
um let's be
honest, you use some very creative ways
to get alcohol, right? I'll be like,
let's be and it's funny because they'll
like sheepishly smile and they'll be
like, yes. And sometimes I'll even say,
you know, tell me some of the stories.
Mhm. And I'm just saying the
brain just the brilliance involved in
getting alcohol like and so I'll say hey
the same brilliance you use to acquire
alcohol now I want you to use that for
your recovery
same brillian same same brilliance you
use to destroy yourself now I want you
to use it to heal yourself so be
creative and and as best you can don't
limit yourself don't just assume I can't
afford recovery when I could afford I
could afford the drug but I can't afford
recovery. All right. Next thing that I
would say is we are all familiar with
alcoholic synonymous. We're all familiar
with it. Yes. And I would say it can
play a powerful role in your recovery.
It really can. Here are some things to
consider. First and
foremost, there tend to be so
many
groups, you can find a group that fits
with your personality. So, just because
you go to the first group and it doesn't
fit, it doesn't mean another group might
not just hit the nail right on the head
and you find a community that supports
you. Now, here's a mistake that some
people can make. they can go to the
group and decide not to work the steps.
[Music]
Okay, it's really important to actually
work the steps. And part of that process
is you got to get a sponsor, right? You
got to get a sponsor, but there's still
a mistake that people can make. So, you
go to the group, you get a sponsor, you
you work the
steps, but what's the mistake then? You
don't graduate to becoming a sponsor.
And and and and those that actually do
graduate to becoming a sponsor, they
have a high rate of maintaining
recovery. Okay. Yeah. So that so so and
it it's free. Uh the it's it's usually
with the mindset of pay it forward, you
know? Right. Yes. Um, and so here's now
now now let's talk about the attitude of
going to the meeting. You could go to
the meeting and sit in the back, right?
Sit in the back where there are a lot of
people who aren't quite as motivated and
you're distracted and you maybe just
leave with somebody who's also not all
that committed. Or you could show up and
you could be present, right? You could
be present. The other thing about the
mindset is you could be looking for
excuses as to why it won't work for you.
You could be looking for excuses and if
you're if you're going in with that
mindset, you're going to find something,
right? But if on the other hand, you
chase your recovery the way you chase
your addiction,
you're not going to let that stuff push
you out. I love that. That's powerful.
Chase your recovery. Chase your recovery
with the same chase your addiction that
you chase your addiction with the same
brilliance with the same creativity.
That's how you chase your recovery.
Don't let anything
dissuade you from your recovery and you
won't be distracted by a lot of the
things that take other people out. I
love that. And you know because you
mentioned um AA meetings and I actually
went to an AA meeting and this was for
school. this is um it was when I was
getting my masters and I we needed to do
um to go to one of those type of
meetings and you know do a paper on and
all this stuff. So but my experience was
I was so impressed with the meeting and
just the community and how I mean
honestly I'll be honest with you the
what I saw at that AA meeting is the way
a very loving healthy
church should be. They were so they like
looked out for each other, encouraged
each other. There was so much love
there. I was like, "Wow." I felt like I
had literally been to church. It was
such a spiritual experience that I
witnessed. I mean, just because they
were, you know, they were giving
testimonies, they were crying, you know,
they were crying because of where
they've come from or just the things
that they've battled, but and other and
some were encouraging those who were
just, you know, starting up. It was just
really like just just a beautiful
experience. I have to say I was I was
impressed. I didn't even know I was
going to do addiction psychiatry, but my
project in medical school was going to
AA meetings. It it surrounded going to
AA meetings. And the thing that was
really cool to me was, you know how in
church you you show up and you and it's
a facade? Like you don't show up to
church and I know exactly what you mean.
I wish I wish it was like this big
bucket where you could take your
sin like put that badge on, right? No,
it's the it's the reverse in church.
It's like there's no label for what your
issue is. But in the 12step meeting,
it's no, this is my
issue. This is my issue. And there's no
judgment. There's no shame. It's just
upfront. No, this is my issue. And
everybody's like, hey man, me too. Hey,
sit down. Let's share. And it's like one
of the first settings
where you don't have to be ashamed,
right? And you're not trying to hide
because you know in church everybody
wants to try to like give their
u you know appearance of yes, I have it
all together. My family, my husband, my
marriage. At a AA meeting, nobody's
trying to even act like that.
It it's just it's it was just such a I
it was just a beautiful thing to
witness. It really was. It was a place
authenticity was celebrated like Yes.
Like so that that was my experience of
it. Um and so that that that was just it
was I I found that very We have a great
question from Joanne here. Um you can
read it if you want. Can someone who is
recovering from Can someone who is a
recovering cocaine addict not using
cocaine for the past 15 years but is now
drinking a lot of year of beers
seemingly not effect can still be
considered an addict or
alcoholic. Well, you got to know in the
recovery community it's it's it's sort
of a all ornone. Now gonna they make an
exception for smoking. I wish they
didn't, you know. Um but like one
exception is made for smoking, but that
aside, any other addiction is viewed as
um uh messing up your recovery, you
know. So, which would make sense for a
cocaine addict and now you're drinking
alcohol, the recovery community would
not be like, "Amen, brother." Like, you
know, no. um that that's not that's not
um that's not celebrated, if you will.
Um it it'd be frowned upon and and and
certainly discouraged
because you're just you're just slipping
to a different addiction when you're
coming going from one to the other. Man,
I could go deeper in this, but even if
they leave leave substances, they might
go to something else
like I don't know like gaming. I don't
know. You know, people get addicted to
sugar like Yeah, something like Yeah,
sugar for sure. Smoking was a big one.
And it's really sad when people succumb
to smoking because
you know alcohol we're saying is killing
about 140,000 people a year. Smoking is
killing
430,000 people a year. Like you really
don't want to succumb to that one.
Um, so I think when you identify an
addiction, it's an opportunity to do a
search to see what is it that I'm
longing for? What what what was it that
this addiction was self-medicating?
And yes,
there will be a temptation to satisfy
the desire with a counterfeit.
Mhm. And you heard it here first. I'm
saying these are counterfeits. These are
counterfeits for your true desire. If
you pay attention 100%. I mean that's
what I share with my clients in therapy.
We I was saying what you just said is
If you pay attention to the core of a
desire, desires tend to be pure. Desires
tend to be pure. Like when you think
about um a longing to be with the
person, all right, that's a pure desire.
When you think of even even alcohol, a
lot of times people start drinking
because they feel nervous when they show
up in a in a public setting. Yeah.
Social anxiety with the social anxiety.
That's pure. Um you take a person who
maybe is using cocaine again like you
you want to feel good. No, that's pure.
And a lot of addiction is a desire to
escape the pain. Yes.
That's pure. Yes. Now the question
before you is will you use a counterfeit
to satisfy the desire.
That's the question.
That's the trick and that's what you
want to avoid. You want to use something
genuine and you want to avoid the
counterfeits. Why a
counterfeit?
Because with a counterfeit, it's not
truly going to satisfy the desire. And
if it does satisfy it, it's a temporary
satisfaction. There's famous quote in
the 12step community. Mhm. One is too
much and a thousand is not enough.
One is too much and a thousand is not
enough. I can't think of a better
description. Me neither. I think that's
a counterfeit.
Absolutely. Absolutely. We have another
comment. Ashley says, "I've been uh in
Alanon since 2015. We are taught not to
control the addict's recovery. I see him
falling back um in and not into old
let's see back in not old patterns and
he relapses. What's the balance? Not
controlling but being supportive. So
she's trying to be a supportive you know
not taking over because that's what
she's taught not to do which is good but
how can she um support? Well, I I think
and you know, sad to say, it sounds like
Melody, the um the author of um of
uh uh Codependent No More, I her her
name is Melody. It's slipping my it's
slipping my I forget. But you answer the
question and I'll look it up. Sincerest,
you know, you know, condolences to that
giant in the field of you know,
addiction and she was just so helpful
with codependent. With codependency,
you're trying to do for someone
something they can do for
themselves. And it's important to
actually control what you can control
what's important. And so this is where
healthy boundaries are important. Um,
and a boundary is useless without a
consequence. So you want to and this is
where some therapeutic reflection can be
helpful. Mhm. Um and that's where what
you can do is you can take some time to
see what will be my boundaries. Okay?
What will be the boundaries that
support, you know, and what will be the
consequences if those boundaries are
violated, right? And it's good to
clarify that and then it's good to
clarify that with that loved one. Um,
and so as you can see, because I don't
know you, I don't know the situation, I
don't know the person in question, I
can't speak really intelligently on it.
And this is why a therapist or someone
with the expertise and custom tailor and
customize a a recommended group of
boundaries, you know, for you. Like you
guys could co-create them and of course
the appropriate consequences. Um, but
that's why it's so uh important. But
that's a that's a great question, right?
And Independent No More was written by
Melody um Beetle. Beetle was it what is
it? Is it Oh, no. No. I'm sorry. Not
Beetle. Betty. Melody. Bey. Bey. Bey or
Betty. Okay. And recently she
unfortunately passed away. So sincerest
condolences uh to to her loved ones uh
that and the addiction community that's
missing her because her book was uh was
a landmark book. Yes, it really was. It
really was. Here's another question. Um
what is the effect of shame and guilt on
someone's recovery? Um came in late and
I don't know if you had talked about it
yet. No, we didn't talk about um shame
and guilt in recovery. Um, David, I'm
going to answer that question. Before I
do that, I'm going to plug the fact that
I am doing a stress uh webinar, a stress
mastery webinar
this Thursday at 700 p.m. Pacific um
this Thursday. So, Amber, I think I sent
you a link to
Yes. And yeah, you guys don't want to
miss this, like I said, because I did
mention it uh at church on Sabbath. So,
you don't want to miss this, guys. And
like I said, uh when I announced it, you
know, we're all dealing with stress and
we can all learn how to better deal with
stress in a healthy way. We will benefit
um our mental health and our physical
health and just our life in general. And
this is uh a free webinar. So, you want
to go there. You definitely want to go
there. Um and I think AMR's working on
getting that up so um you guys will know
where to go. So, for those of you just
in case we don't get the link, um,
info@themastermind institute. Just email
me at info@themastermind institute and I
will send the, um, the link over to you
again. Info at the mastermind institute.
All right. Now, let me answer um, let me
answer uh, David's question. What is the
effect of shame um, and guilt? See, this
is
why it is so
important to limit the focus on shame
and even on guilt. Because when you when
you really focus on shame and guilt, one
of the things it will do is it can
actually trigger a relapse. You can feel
so ashamed and so worthless. Remember,
addiction is a disease of escape. So,
you can feel so awful, guess what? You
want to escape feeling awful and you end
up succumbing. You end up actually um
you can end up relapsing. So, what I'm
getting at, David, is there's a point at
which
uh shame and guilt
uh there's a point at which shame and
guilt can actually like not help you.
Uh, and so you want to be aware of that.
Um, I'm
checking that's that that link is not
me. Uh, uh, Amra, I mean, this is me. Is
that not your link? The mastermind
Institute.com.
It's it's the mastermind, not Oh, the
mastermind. There you go. I don't know
if that's the link for
um the mastermind. Okay. for the thing.
But anyway, so I just want you to think
about that and maybe you can make a
comment while I get him the while I get
Ammer the link. Okay. Yeah, you can get
the correct correct link out there. Um
let's see. We have
other comments
um and questions. Let's see.
Um Shereice again wants to know, I have
a friend who makes his own beer.
Hm. What's the advice can be given
concerning his alcoholic tendencies if
he can make his
own? I mean, it's still beer, so I don't
think it I mean, it I don't think it it
matters if he
um if he can make it. I don't know if
I'm completely understanding the
question, but whether he gets it at a
store, if he makes it, if he's addicted
to it or cannot stop, um all the
principles stay the same.
Um, the first time I saw the name
spirits um, mentioned on a store that
sold alcohol, I was clueless. But they
don't hide what it is. Um, I agree. I
mean, growing up, I didn't really
realize what um, them calling it
spirits. Um, but it really is. um it can
really medicate the mind um and and to
take over um our the way that we would
normally think when we're not um
intoxicated with alcohol or any really
um any drug. Um so I think but I think
spirits is definitely the correct um a
good name for
it. So yeah, there's there's a lot of
different um did you want to say
something Dr. Wy with the prior
question? with the prayer question,
view the addiction as an opportunity to
go on a journey to solve the real issue.
And let's say for example, as opposed to
drinking their alcohol milk, well, maybe
I'll make my own. That that's still
using a substitute. It's still using um
a counterfeit. So,
um I I I think it would be worth, you
know, exploring what is it that I'm
really after? Like, um I think I think
that's what addictions steal from us and
or that's what counterfeits steal from
us, right? Is the ability to find out
what am I really what am I really after?
What is what is my true desire? It's a
worthwhile journey. I mean it is just
what is it that I truly desire because I
think that'll be incredibly powerful.
Um there's definitely people who are
appreciating this topic. I know David
Hunt says that uh he's appreciating this
and he'll have to go back and listen to
the whole thing. Um but it is a very um
important topic and um go just kind of
piggybacking off of what Dr. White said
again. do share. I'm not an addiction um
counselor specialist. I don't specialize
in addiction, but um I of course I do um
I'm dealing with clients who are dealing
with different health mental health
issues with anxiety, depression, and
they also are addicted to some
substance, whether that's weed or
cigarettes or these different things.
And when we're doing, you know, talk
therapy, um, you know, where we start to
get into what are some of those base
issues, like you said, what are some of
the feelings that you're trying to numb
through, um, taking these different
substances? Um, and so dealing with that
and going to the core foundation of
these issues, I find, is is very helpful
in the recovery process of recovering
from any um, addiction. Um, and because
a lot of times people start at such a
young age and covering up these emotions
and just not wanting to feel the pain of
that or think about that. And if I can,
you know, take a hit of something or
drink something or smoke something uh
that will make me forget about it, they
will continue to do that every single
day. So, when we go and get to the root
issues, it really can help um give some
freedom and some relief. And that's not
taking away from going to like a rehab
and things like that, but it is helping
to deal with the core issue of why you
started down this path in the first
place. Dr. White, well, I'll tell you
something interesting. So from time to
time I remember in in treating uh
someone with addiction um they may have
had a loved one who passed away uh let's
say like a year ago but they had
escalated their drinking shortly after
that person passed away and now in
treatment where they've been
detoxed. It's as if they're crying about
it that like their their grief
experience is as if it happened
yesterday.
Um as if the death happened yesterday.
Now, why would that be? Because it's
almost as if the substance, the
counterfeit had interfered with their
ability to process the grief, to
experience the grief.
And that's how
profoundly we can be impacted by relying
on a counterfeit. Once you remove that
counterfeit, it's waiting for you. It's
right there waiting for you. So now
Joanne said, "I'm trying to figure out
how to let that individual know that
drinking alcohol is a counterfeit of
cocaine. Will he be offended or feel
defeated?"
Well, Joanne, these are the questions I
would need to know in order to answer
that question. I would, and I'm not
asking to know them. I'm just like
letting you know why I can't why it's
hard to answer that question. I don't
know your relationship with the person.
I don't know if you have listened to
them enough to build the credibility to
where they would award you with having
influence over them. Um I I don't know
your understanding of addiction or
recovery. Um so I hope you just see
there is just a litany of things that go
into making a recommendation to a
person. And the first is you have to be
perceived as credible by that person.
And part of being perceived as credible
is being knowledgeable on the issue.
Number two is them being clear. You're
emotionally invested in them and them
feeling like you've listened to me
enough.
The to the point where I'm literally
asking you, hey, what are your thoughts?
What are your thoughts? And what you'll
find is people will often make
recommendations
prior to having earned the right to make
those recommendations. So I think
Joanne's follow-up question then would
be well what can I do you know and
that's why that's why the professional
consultation would be so critical
because there is something to be done
yes and I'm not I'm not minimizing
prayer I'm a I I I believe prayer
changes things um but I think that more
can be done but I I want you to see why
professional consultation is critical
because then you can customize it to the
situation. You can right happen. Hi
Ashley,
I'm very sick right now having seizures
and being unable to enforce boundaries
because I need his help and I have no
other support. How can I navigate follow
through on boundaries? Boy, Ashley, that
was powerful. Um, your statement on
seizures is an important reminder about
why. Oh, and I'm not saying, by the way,
that this is like alcohol related. I'm
just saying seizures triggers my
recollection of something that we want
to kind of warn you about, right? Um,
sometimes there are people who they've
been drinking a lot of alcohol and then
for some reason they decide they just
want to stop abruptly. And that is
incredibly dangerous to abruptly stop
alcohol outside of the care of
professionals
um and and medical professionals. And
the reason is is because it puts a
person at risk for seizures
um strokes, heart attacks, that kind of
stuff because it can be incredibly
dangerous during withdrawal, especially
if you're outside of medical care. There
are things that need to be managed.
There are conditions that need to be
managed um that sometimes it's not
obvious. I remember when I was detoxing
patients, we were dealing with things
like their blood pressure shooting up,
heart rate shooting up massively. Um and
we would have to medicate them. we would
have to treat them with something that
simulated alcohol and then we would
taper them off to safely get them
through their uh their withdrawal
period. Um so
Ash, thank Ashley because it reminded me
just to talk about that a little bit.
But this Ashley I mean this is
complicated. that situation is
incredibly um complicated and it
definitely warrants getting some
professional support. Now, I've said
that many times and so some of you may
wonder, okay, well, let's say I'm on a
shoestring budget and but I need
professional help. What are resources
that would be available to me? A lot of
times you can get some pretty excellent
resources at the county level. Okay. So,
out here for me it's the county of San
Bernardino. Um there's adjacent to it
county of Riverside. And these counties
really um try to empower themselves to
be able to meaningfully impact a
population and address their mental
health needs including their addiction
needs. So, I would definitely
investigate at the county level what's
available to me. Obviously, if you're
insured, you want to contact your
insurance and check in and see um what
is available to you. You can go to your
primary care doctor and you can again
you can ask and find out, hey, what's
available to me? What might be a
therapist that is that that actually has
expertise in this area? Um then of
course there's your 12step communities.
sometimes in the 12step communities
again you might learn about resources
that are you know available in in in
your in your area. Um but Ashley super
complicated question. Thank you for the
courage of you know asking a question
like that. Um but it it really deserves
some customized attention. Yes. Okay.
This is going to be our last question
but definitely let's take this. Since I
stopped using drugs and alcohol, I feel
like I've lost touch with my
intellectual feelings. But in addition,
two and a half years ago when I was
still using, I was stabbed in a coma for
and I was in a coma for um three days.
Let's see. So, lack of oxygen in
addition to copious amounts of drugs
have played a role in my memory loss as
well as what seems to be uh dissociative
disorder. Any thoughts on that?
So, Christopher, um, if I were you, uh,
I would pick up the book, um, The Brain
That Changes Itself. The brain that
changes itself, um, because I would be I
would be investing in in personal mental
health rehab. I would be stimulating my
brain like crazy. I would be trying to
learn languages. I'd be trying to learn,
you know, different activities. I would
I would be communicating to my brain,
I'm not done with you, right? I'm not
done with the neuroplasticity and it can
happen. I would be triggering
neuroplasticity. In that book that I'm
recommending to you, the brain that
changes itself, it has these amazing
stories of people who had suffered like
massive strokes. you're talking about
like anoxic injuries and I'm not I'm not
minimizing that but these are people who
suffered massive strokes but because
their rehab was so aggressive they were
able to get amazing recoveries amazing
recoveries um but just the idea but the
general picture of what I'm describing
Christopher is I would really want to
stimulate my brain I would want to
challenge my brain I'd want to read I'd
want to think I'd want to memorize
scripture I would want to learn
languages. I would tell me what you do
for a living. Uh Christopher, um just it
it'll kind of help me kind of frame my
my advice to you, but I would um I I
would really want to, you know, stretch
my brain. um right being patient and
loving with it because I'm not saying
overwhelm it, but I just mean as much as
it would allow me to, I would want to
grow and I would want to get better at
my activities. I would want to really
apply myself. Um because the brain is
capable of change. We are gifted with a
neuroplastic brain and it it tends to to
to have the ability to help us with the
activity of our choosing. It's the most
beautiful gift I feel like that God gave
us in our body. He's a farmer and a
carpenter for the past 20 years. So, I
would be I would be developing I'd be
trying to learn new aspects of of of
carpentry, you know, as much as it's
safe or whatever, you know, because I
don't I don't know your particular
situation, but I'd really want to be
trying to develop my skill to become
really proficient. I'd want to do
everything I could to communicate to my
brain, I'm not done with you. And talk
about the vitamins that I'd be going
after. I want I would want to just love
on my brain with nutrients. Love on my
brain with sleep, love on my brain with
oxygen. Um uh so you got your B12, you
got I mean it's just and and YouTube is
right there. So there's so much we do
research to find out. Oh, there's so
much my brain um the brain canate.
That's right. Yeah. There's the book
right there. The brain that changes
itself. It's beautiful. It's beautiful.
Yes, the book is beautiful.
Well, um I'm glad you guys loved this
topic um because yeah, it's been a you
know, it's was great um to share with
you this evening. Uh there's so much
there and and there's still um possibly
more to talk about. We will be back next
week and so look out uh for that, but
definitely share this on your social
media. Share it with your on your social
media with your family and friends. um
because even if they're not struggling
with this themselves personally, they
have a friend or a loved one that they
can um learn and and to grow and just to
just to have this knowledge for
themselves. So definitely share this on
your social media. And thank you again
Dr. White. Thank you so well for being
our
producer behind the scen. Yeah, don't
forget the stress mastery webinar this
Thursday at 700 p.m. Pacific. 7 PM
Pacific. You know, I know we're all
stressed out. Come out. It's free. Yeah,
it's free. I think we're going to put it
up there again. I think that's going to
go back up there so you guys can see
that. And um yeah, I think it's going
back up there. But it's uh the the
master the
mastermindstitute.com/webinar and you'll
be able to get that information. Um and
if you missed that, we put it up before
you can always do the replay and play
this back so you can see. So don't miss
it. Tell your friends. Tell your friends
because there is stress everywhere.
Everywhere. Yes, it's in the chat there.
So definitely click that link. Be safe
everyone. Always a pleasure. Always a
pleasure. I'll see you next week. We'll
see you next week. Bring a friend. Bring
a family member. Uh we love to see you
here on Mental Health Monday. Have a
good evening. Bye-bye. Thank you. Till
next time.